<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
	<title>edibotopic | blog</title>
	<subtitle>Writing on food, technology and philosophy</subtitle>
	<link href="https://edibotopic.com/blog/thinking/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://edibotopic.com/blog/thinking/"/>
	<updated>2023-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	<id>https://edibotopic.com/blog/thinking/feed.xml</id>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Misdirected Science: Untested Claims and their Derivative Tangents</title>
		<published>2023-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2023-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <summary>&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s a kind of applied science that bothers me. It starts with
some extravagant claim that is made by a researcher. This then
encourages other researchers to pursue a set of loosely-related
questions that don&#x27;t test the original claim. The material importance
of these derivative questions then becomes &lt;em&gt;conditional&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; on the truth of
that initial and untested claim.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</summary>
		<link href="https://edibotopic.com/blog/thinking/misdirected-science/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://edibotopic.com/blog/thinking/misdirected-science/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s a kind of applied science that bothers me. It starts with
some extravagant claim that is made by a researcher. This then
encourages other researchers to pursue a set of loosely-related
questions that don&#x27;t test the original claim. The material importance
of these derivative questions then becomes &lt;em&gt;conditional&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; on the truth of
that initial and untested claim.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;continue-reading&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This situation is distinct from pure, &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;blog&#x2F;on-interestingness&quot;&gt;curiosity-driven
research&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. The research questions are not
necessarily interesting &lt;em&gt;in themselves&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. They &lt;em&gt;would be&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; interesting
&lt;strong&gt;if&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; the original claim was demonstrably true. The research is
motivated and constrained by a mere &lt;em&gt;unlikely possibility&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, which
becomes a flimsy axiom&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; undergirding the entire research effort.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years ago a scientist approached me about a potential
collaboration. There had been big excitement about a particular new
technology. Another scientist had claimed that a consumer product could
be responsible for an unusually wide range of health issues affecting
human populations.
This scientist was proposing that they had identified the source of the
health issue (a consumer product) as well as the technology that could 
solve the problem (a replacement product).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Significant time had passed since this claim was made and there was
still little supporting evidence. The (lack of) mechanistic
justification for the claim had been roundly criticised by the
scientific community. That the scientist who made the
original claim had since built a company that already
profited from selling their &amp;quot;healthier&amp;quot; replacement of the consumer
product fuelled additional skepticism.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my office, my colleague and I both shared the view that the
original claim was likely bogus. They reminded me, however, that there
was a lot of interest in this topic and that it could be the basis of
a lucrative funding proposal. My colleague assured me that while the
work would focus on the product in question and its &amp;quot;healthier&amp;quot; replacement,
none of our research would relate directly to the controversial question of 
health effects.
The exciting and controversial health question was merely a shiny vessel in
which we could smuggle our more dull and legitimate scientific questions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The focus of all this attention was a commercial food product&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;, and it
was claimed that it was a major contributor to human disease. &lt;em&gt;If that
was true&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, some healthier alternatives would need to be developed. As
scientists, we might focus on enhancing the flavour and texture of
alternatives, such that &lt;em&gt;in the event that they were needed&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; people
might find them tolerable to consume. This is a common tendency in
food science because many food scientists do not have the expertise to
study health effects: a product will generate interest and prestige
because of its health effects (real or imagined) and food scientists
will study everything but those health effects.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aura of the original health-claim — still untested yet now the
subject of intense marketing efforts — imbued all derivative research
projects with urgency and importance. Funding proposals, press
releases and lectures relating to such research projects lead with the
premise that the technology under investigation &lt;em&gt;could&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; be a major
factor in human disease. It became apparent in the conversation with
my colleague that even if the original claim was likely false there
was now growing commercial incentives fuelled by that claim. There
were companies who wanted to invest in the manufacture of these
&amp;quot;healthy&amp;quot; alternatives. To implement them effectively &lt;em&gt;good science&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;
was required and so funding was being made available by governments
and corporations.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the philosophical sense&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, this kind of scientific rhetoric is
&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.thecollector.com&#x2F;revisiting-bullshit-harry-frankfurt-essay&#x2F;&quot;&gt;bullshit&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
It is fundamentally unconcerned with the truth of the claim that
motivates and justifies the whole research effort. Scientists conform
to the ideas set forth in the claim simply because it suits their
purposes.
This is corrosive to the pursuit of truth even if some
science gets done in the process.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#x27;s consider briefly why this might be an undesirable set of circumstances:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other real problems of actual consequence exist and need to be solved.
Given the existence of real problems that are known to affect people
right now then these should be the focus of investment and research,
not possible issues that can be reasonably assumed to not exist.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public perception is influenced by the rhetoric of science. If a
technology is being marketed as important then scientific research on
the technology that doesn&#x27;t test its efficacy directly, and even
&lt;em&gt;assumes passively that it is efficacious&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, may lend unwarranted
scientific legitimacy to that technology.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In popular discourse there is sometimes a skepticism about applied
sciences like food science. I think these criticisms are often
grandiose and unfounded, frequently missing the important
contributions that these sciences have made to society. However, I
think that there is sometimes a cynicism and opportunism in how
scientists choose their projects, especially when the scientific
problems relate to a technology of potential commercial value.
Technologies making extraordinary claims come and go by the dozen.
Some eventually shrink their claims in response to regulatory
scrutiny&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#3&quot;&gt;3&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. In the intervening period — which can span many years —
scientists help shape the perception of technology, among students,
funders and the public. They therefore have some responsibility for
considering the impact of their choices, in terms of public
understanding of science, the effective use of resources and the
perceived societal role of their own discipline.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I explained to the scientist&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#4&quot;&gt;4&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; that I was not interested in
researching the technology. They later received funding for their
project. It was a bad career decision on my part and I&#x27;m glad I made
it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a mathematical proof an axiom is taken to be a self-evident
truth, stipulated so that the proof can be constructed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do not want to focus on the product itself but rather the
general issue it represents.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;3&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A claim to treat a disease may become a promise of providing more &amp;quot;comfort&amp;quot;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnote-definition&quot; id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-definition-label&quot;&gt;4&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lovely person and great colleague by the way.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Making Things Strange: An Inverse Problem in Teaching</title>
		<published>2023-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2023-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <summary>&lt;p&gt;It is common to explain the unfamiliar by reference to the
familiar, but when teaching a quotidian science (&lt;em&gt;of the everyday&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;) this explanatory mode is
inverted.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</summary>
		<link href="https://edibotopic.com/blog/thinking/strange-food-pedagogy/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://edibotopic.com/blog/thinking/strange-food-pedagogy/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is common to explain the unfamiliar by reference to the
familiar, but when teaching a quotidian science (&lt;em&gt;of the everyday&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;) this explanatory mode is
inverted.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;continue-reading&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;strange-ideas&quot;&gt;Strange Ideas&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#strange-ideas&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: strange-ideas&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many are mystified and threatened by the &lt;em&gt;algorithm&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.
This word is most typically invoked in discussions about 
the black boxes that digest our data and spit out personalised
feeds, advertisements and recommendations.
The inner workings of the black box are complex
and often proprietary, maintaining their distance
and strangeness.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$input \xrightarrow{black \ box} output$$&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;algorithm&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is a more general tool than the discourse suggests,
with applications that extend far beyond e-commerce and social media.
Students of programming usually take a course in algorithms.
Here they learn how to write code that prints sequences of
characters to the screen or calculates statistics for a dataset.
Later they encounter more complex algorithms that can help
simulate enemy movement in video games or — indeed — generate
personalised recommendations for a vast social network.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The generality of a tool like the algorithm lies in its abstractness.
Conceptual and underspecified, its implementations apply to a broad
class of particular cases.
Mathematical operations like &lt;code&gt;sum&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; are similarly abstract.
We can conceive of summing a collection of physical objects, summing
a set of
integers or a summing millilitres of liquid.
In a computer program, a simple algorithm
would be employed to implement the
concept of a&lt;code&gt;sum&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When teaching there is tendency to appeal first to concrete 
instances rather than directly engaging with an abstract concept.
The first model of the algorithm that many encounter is the recipe.
To develop an understanding we direct knowledge
from a familiar, concrete &lt;em&gt;source&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (recipes) to an unfamiliar, abstract &lt;em&gt;target&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;
(algorithms)
through the invocation of metaphor (or analogy):&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$source \xrightarrow{metaphor} target$$&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;appealing-to-the-familiar&quot;&gt;Appealing to the Familiar&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#appealing-to-the-familiar&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: appealing-to-the-familiar&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;The Art of Computer Programming&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; the computer scientist
Donald Knuth (1968) explained how an algorithm is analogous to a recipe.
Just like a recipe, it takes a finite amount of inputs and produces
a specific output.
This transformation requires that a sequence of steps be first
defined and then carried out in a particular order.
It can be expected that Knuth&#x27;s analogy (like all analogies) will
crumble at some point; for now, it is enough for us to &amp;quot;grasp&amp;quot;
at the abstract concept in a useful way.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as a cook follows a recipe to produce a meal, a computer
processes code to produce a desired output, which could be a
successful calculation or a graphical representation.
For some computer scientists, the salient distinction between these
two kinds of procedures is the degree to which the instructions can 
be said to have precision.
A recipe — they assume — is prone to ambiguity and may yield
different results depending on who interprets its steps.
The education of a programmer then places a strong emphasis on
achieving precision when defining the goals of a program,
articulating clearly the structure of the requisite code and
testing effectively the reliability of its performance.
As a teacher I am fascinated by this bait-and-switch
as pedagogical rhetoric.
&lt;em&gt;Coding is like cooking.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This is a model of cooking and how it maps to our concept of programming.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;You are programmers not cooks&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.
&lt;em&gt;Here is why our programs must never be merely like recipes.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most programs are composed of functions,
small self-contained procedures that transform
a set of inputs into an output.
A calculator is a program that can perform
different kinds of mathematical operations,
each defined by an appropriate function (sum, multiply, divide).
&amp;quot;Pure&amp;quot; functions in programming are essentially
the same as mathematical functions.
They map a set of inputs from a source domain
to a target codomain.
In a pure function, like &lt;code&gt;sum_two_numbers&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;,
given multiple inputs (&lt;code&gt;2, 3&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;) there is only
one output (&lt;code&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;).
The function &lt;code&gt;sum_two_numbers&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; should achieve
the same transformation in all contexts.
It will always map the same two numbers
in the source domain to one number in the
codomain.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$domain \xrightarrow{function} codomain$$&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process of cooking a meal can also be understood
as being composed of smaller procedures.
A meal consists a combination of materials,
each of which has been transformed by an
appropriate procedure (peeling, mixing, heating).
However, a cooking procedure may yield different
outputs dependent on context.
For example, two people may have varying degrees
of skill and&#x2F;or may interpret the instructions
differently.
On this limited account, a cooking procedure is further
from the Platonic ideal of a mathematical function than a computer
program, assuming that such programs consist strictly of &lt;em&gt;pure&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; functions 
(and most — in fact — do not).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$recipe \xrightarrow{interpret \ \&amp;amp; \ act} meal$$&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside, it should be noted that the distinction between technical
(computational) and nontechnical (culinary) procedures that
privileges the former as more &lt;strong&gt;effective&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; has been challenged by
some theoretical computer scientists (see Cleland, 2001).
In addition, practitioners in fields like molecular
gastronomy assert that great precision
can be achieved when cooking, if certain rules and principles are
followed, perhaps resulting in a more &lt;em&gt;algorithmic&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; cookery.
As Dan Cox suggests in a blog in
&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;videlais.com&#x2F;2020&#x2F;08&#x2F;15&#x2F;code-stories-recipe&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Digital
Ephemera&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
understanding through metaphor might
operate in a bidirectional manner, rather
than the strictly unidirectional $source \to target$ scheme:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across the &lt;strong&gt;bridge&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; of metaphor,
recipe and algorithm might have
more to &lt;strong&gt;offer each other&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; in comparison 
than appears at first glance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;bridge&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; here is an apt (meta)metaphor itself, in that
we may return from a destination via the
same route that we have travelled there.
Thinking of &lt;em&gt;algorithms as recipes&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; prompts
us to consider &lt;em&gt;recipes as algorithms&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.
Laying a metaphor between two domains
implies the formation of a
&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Hermeneutic_circle&quot;&gt;loop of interpretation&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; through which there is 
the possibility of better understanding both. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;making-things-weird&quot;&gt;Making Things Weird&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#making-things-weird&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: making-things-weird&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The challenge for the teacher of abstract concepts
is the translation of the strange to the familiar (at least initially).
Food, ingredients and recipes are common sources of analogy and
metaphor in these cases, and not only with algorithms as the target (Crowley, 2022).
An everyday concept is leveraged to transform
the strange or abstract new idea into something
more familiar.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$strange \xrightarrow{pedagogy} familiar$$&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that this transformation is often inverted when teaching a 
quotidian science.
By &amp;quot;quotidian science&amp;quot; I mean a science that has an everyday
object as its focus.
My specialisation — food science — is such a quotidian science.
The inverse problem involves transforming the
familiar objects of daily life into something
strange and new.
Achieving this transformation may coincide
with the overcoming of significant resistance,
due to these familiar ideas being so &lt;em&gt;baked in&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A novice student of food science has a high degree of familiarity
with the material that they intend to study.
Eating, cooking and dieting are mundane concepts.
When learning the science of food they experience the familiar becoming
strange, which can be a disturbing process.
While explaining the strange in terms of the familiar is
a common pedagogical tool, a disturbing rendering of the familiar as
strange has more often been associated with artistic work. 
On one interpretation (Shklovsky, 1917), this is the fundamental goal of art: to show 
us the objects of reality in an altered form, such that we return
to the world with a more enriched sense of the objects &lt;em&gt;as they are&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shklovsky&#x27;s idea — known as &lt;strong&gt;defamiliarisation&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; — is an arcane concept borrowed from
art criticism, yet I think it is close in spirit
to how many scientific educators and communicators conceive of their role.
Scientists can be sensitive to the claim (scientism) that they are iconoclasts,
who destroy everyday symbols that comfort and enthrall us.
Richard Feynman famously rejected the idea that his scientific
worldview ruined the beauty of a flower, suggesting instead that
&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.themarginalian.org&#x2F;2013&#x2F;01&#x2F;01&#x2F;ode-to-a-flower-richard-feynman&#x2F;&quot;&gt;science only served to enrich his appreciation of that beauty&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
This is a useful reminder that new theoretical knowledge can
enrich — rather than displace — everyday intuition.
A two-step process (or loop) can be imagined, in which the familiar is made
strange (conceptually) before we return to the familiar (in
reality) and appreciate it in a new aspect.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$1. \ familiar \xrightarrow{defamiliarisation} strange$$&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$2. \ familiar \xleftarrow{enrichment} strange$$&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scientific and the everyday coexist and interact productively.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;defamiliarisers&quot;&gt;Defamiliarisers&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#defamiliarisers&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: defamiliarisers&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientists, like artists, can alter how we perceive the world.
As communicators, they often play the role of defamiliarisers.
Their lessons can enrich our experience and intellect, or they can 
damage our sense of how we relate to reality, leading to a rejection
of science or even a descent into conspiracy theories.
The outcome may depend on how effectively the scientist
communicates and how their audience understands their motives.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tools that move us between the familiar and the strange — like
metaphor and analogy — are
central to explanation, whether through artistic epiphany or
scientific discovery.
Understanding art as a force for defamiliarisation does not necessarily
mean that artists destroy everyday conceptions of the
world.
Instead, through art (and science) such intuitions can be retained while being enriched.
It is possible to know the pain of bureaucracy without reading
&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Franz_Kafka&quot;&gt;Kafka&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, but reading 
&lt;em&gt;The Trial&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; will certainly make you experience
that same pain in new and interesting ways!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In science communication, there is perhaps a greater
rhetorical emphasis on actively changing minds and
correcting falsities.
Sometimes this clarity of focus is demanded in the
context of a live crisis.
In more normal times, it might be wise to use our scientific truths
to enrich the everyday and mundane and not seek to displace them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#references&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: references&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cleland, C. (2001). Recipes, algorithms, and programs. &lt;em&gt;Minds and
Machines&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, 11, 219-237.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crowley, S. V. (2022). Alchemical and cyborgian imaginings in technoscientific discourse relating to holistic turns in food processing and personalised nutrition. In &lt;em&gt;Metaphor, Sustainability, Transformation&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. I. Hughes, E. Byrne, G. Mullaly., &amp;amp; C. Sage (Eds.). Routledge. 65-97.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knuth, D. E. (1997&#x2F;1968). &lt;em&gt;The Art of Computer Programming&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (3rd ed). Addison-Wesley.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shklovsky, V. (1988&#x2F;1917). Art as Device. In &lt;em&gt;Modern Criticism and Theory:
A Reader&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. L. T. Lemon and M. J. Reis (Trans.), David Lodge (Ed.). Longmans. 16-30.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>On Valuing the Merely Interesting</title>
		<published>2023-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2023-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <summary>&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve been contemplating whether there is a place for the &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; interesting in research and teaching.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</summary>
		<link href="https://edibotopic.com/blog/thinking/on-interestingness/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://edibotopic.com/blog/thinking/on-interestingness/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve been contemplating whether there is a place for the &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; interesting in research and teaching.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;continue-reading&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years ago an academic journal named &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.journalofcontroversialideas.org&quot;&gt;The Journal of Controversial Ideas&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; was created. It offers a platform for authors to explore ideas that traditional outlets might reject due to their controversial nature. That a &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; controversial idea would not necessarily warrant academic publication seems unproblematic. We can assume, however, that this new journal is not intended to platform &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; controversial ideas. The editors are likely seeking presentations of ideas that are both controversial &lt;em&gt;and&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; valuable in some way. The &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; qualifier does a lot of work here and elsewhere. Take the philosopher Kant&#x27;s &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;plato.stanford.edu&#x2F;entries&#x2F;kant-moral&quot;&gt;second formulation of his categorical imperative&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So act that you use humanity, whether in your own person or in the person of any other, always at the same time as an end, never &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; as a means&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Kant&#x27;s ethics we should not treat individuals (and ourselves) as &lt;em&gt;mere&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; means but as &lt;em&gt;ends&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in themselves. The student of ethics prematurely dismisses this maxim as &amp;quot;unrealistic&amp;quot;, insofar as we must frequently use people when conducting a variety of daily tasks. While Kantian ethics prohibits instrumentalising people it does not forbid us from paying for services or asking for favours. These routine social interactions can be navigated successfully without disregarding the dignity of others. During business hours, we may use a worker as a means of obtaining some service but we should also reimburse them fairly and treat them with respect. If we were to meet again outside of that specific business context then it would be inappropriate for us to continue to treat that individual as a worker by asking them to provide that same service. In such a way we can treat someone as a means but usually not as a &lt;em&gt;mere&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; means, while — in contrast — we use an object like a hammer &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; as a tool and pay it no higher deference.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On encountering the new journal I imagined a better journal might have been &lt;em&gt;The Journal of Interesting Ideas&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. The title would itself be a more controversial gesture to the academic world, as it suggests that the existing ecosystem of journals is somewhat &lt;em&gt;biased against interesting ideas&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. This might be a surprising claim, given that we surely expect academic journals to support and encourage interesting ideas. Writing a scientific paper that is interesting, however, is usually a necessary but not sufficient condition for it to be publishable. Most of my professional work is in science, where journals are unlikely to publish an interesting hypothesis unless it is accompanied by a sound theoretical foundation and&#x2F;or rigorous attempt at experimental falsification. Scientific journals then would appear to have a reasonable bias against the &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; interesting, just as they have a reasonable bias against the &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; controversial. When someone advocates for more research in &lt;em&gt;basic&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; science or the pursuit of &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;theconversation.com&#x2F;academics-fear-the-value-of-knowledge-for-its-own-sake-is-diminishing-75341&quot;&gt;knowledge-for-knowledge&#x27;s sake&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; they usually do so in the tacit expectation that such work will be conducted in adherence with standards of rigor and therefore not suffer the fate of being &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; interesting.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the work described is [merely] interesting it is not publishable in its current form.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— A common reviewer comment in a rejection letter&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do sometimes wonder if more attention ought to be given to the &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; interesting in discussions of science, as it so often &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;web.mit.edu&#x2F;redingtn&#x2F;www&#x2F;netadv&#x2F;SP20151130.html&quot;&gt;provides the inspiration for scientific discovery&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and sustains it through prolonged periods of frustration and difficulty. Experiments yield interesting scientific facts but only after an interesting question has first been asked. There are innumerable scientific ideas swirling in the minds of scientists and echoing through the corridors of science departments, many of which might go unexplored for a variety of practical reasons. They exist in the realm of the &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; interesting, relegated to coffee speculations and classroom tangents. Even in fallow periods, with a desperate lack of funding and&#x2F;or personnel, it is an essential aspect of the scientist&#x27;s job to &lt;em&gt;become interested&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in something and find a means of developing that interest. A &lt;em&gt;Journal of Merely Interesting Ideas&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; could be useful in such cases. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least in science, there is little pedagogical treatment of the notion of &lt;em&gt;interestingness&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in the development of an idea. Students are drilled in how to conduct experiments but not how to find or identify interesting scientific questions. A student will sometimes become perplexed when I invite them to &amp;quot;find what interests you&amp;quot; in a scientific work, as if pleading with me to explain &lt;em&gt;what it means to find something &amp;quot;interesting&amp;quot; in science&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. I am reminded of the French semiotician Roland Barthes&#x27; distinction between the &lt;em&gt;studium&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (the set of elements in a work and the context of its presentation) and the &lt;em&gt;punctum&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (a piercing detail in a work that moves or intrigues) in &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Camera_lucida&quot;&gt;Camera Lucida: Reflections on Photography&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. All scientific papers have the same basic structure and ask a typically narrow set of questions in relation to a specific problem (&lt;em&gt;studium&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;) but some papers owe their longevity to a minor detail, throwaway comment or experimental error that attracts the interest of the scientific reader (&lt;em&gt;punctum&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;). It might be unfair to expect students to be familiar with this unusual manner of reading, especially when it typically goes unarticulated.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It does not seem to me that science in any strict way &lt;em&gt;depends&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; on controversy, at least not as much as it depends on interestingness. There are — of course — famous examples of the stifled pursuit of ideas that were deemed controversial (&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.newscientist.com&#x2F;article&#x2F;mg13618460-600-vatican-admits-galileo-was-right&#x2F;&quot;&gt;see the Galileo affair&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;), which compel us to protect the free pursuit of ideas and to remain cautious about unchecked institutional power. Yet, while controversy can certainly be an impediment to the pursuit or expression of an idea, the greatest impediment of all is simply to never become interested in an idea in the first instance. It would perhaps be a greater historical tragedy if Galileo had failed to become sufficiently motivated to make discoveries as he looked upon the universe with disinterest.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>