<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
	<title>edibotopic</title>
	<subtitle>food | technology | philosophy</subtitle>
	<link href="https://edibotopic.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://edibotopic.com"/>
	<updated>2023-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	<id>https://edibotopic.com/feed.xml</id>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Converting Images to 3D Models</title>
		<published>2023-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2023-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <summary>&lt;p&gt;I made a simple web-based tool for converting grayscale images to 3D models.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</summary>
		<link href="https://edibotopic.com/blog/write-height/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://edibotopic.com/blog/write-height/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I made a simple web-based tool for converting grayscale images to 3D models.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;continue-reading&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Far more powerful software than this tool — &lt;em&gt;WriteHeight&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; — exist but their complexity often presents a significant barrier to newcomers.
Based solely on heightmaps, WriteHeight only requires the user to upload or draw grayscale images.
The 2D image is then converted into a 3D model that can be inspected or downloaded.
This post explains the motivation behind WriteHeight, what it can do and why it still needs a lot of work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Play around with &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;edibotopic.github.io&#x2F;write-height&#x2F;&quot;&gt;WriteHeight&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;edibotopic&#x2F;write-height&quot;&gt;read the source code&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;making-3d-easier&quot;&gt;Making 3D Easier&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While not everyone self-identifies as an artist people still draw in a variety of contexts.
I work mostly with scientists who — while not usually artistically-trained — routinely produce drawings in the form of flow diagrams and graphical abstracts.
Whether generated on paper or on a screen, these drawings are an important method of thinking through our ideas and communicating them to others. Concepts can also be represented in 3D, but this traditionally requires a mastery of techniques like shading and perspective.
Today, powerful (and free) software like &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;edibotopic.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;write-height&#x2F;www.blender.com&quot;&gt;Blender&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; allows the direct manipulation of models in 3D space, and there is an endless supply of online learning resources to get people started.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My initial forays into 3D were prompted by online teaching.
The difficulty in the remote delivery of STEM content lies more with the laboratory practicals than the lectures, and I wanted to learn how to make interactive 3D versions of these labs.
At the same time, I was involved in research projects on the 3D printing of food.
Whether in the context of teaching or research, I found that scientists were reluctant to engage with 3D modelling.
Research papers on topics like 3D food printing often give minimal attention to the design of a given model or the specific purpose of its structure.
The apparent discomfort with 3D design is perhaps unsurprising, given that the transition from 2D to 3D introduces marked complexity.
A 3D scene can require the management of new kinds of elements — like cameras and lights — that are not required when making a 2D image.
Well-constructed scenes can look ugly if the lighting is wrong.
A model may not render or print correctly if the topology is flawed. 
There are different paradigms of modelling, including the direct modelling approach favoured by digital artists and the parametric approach used by mechanical engineers.
Blender is also a hybrid application — combining (at a minimum) a 3D modeller, animation suite, video editor and compositor — and this vast range of functionality is evident in its interface.
Despite all these complexities, much can be learned about 3D modelling from adept teenagers with small YouTube channels.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;figs&#x2F;writeHeightUI.png&quot; alt=&quot;UI of WriteHeight&quot; title=&quot;UI of WriteHeight&quot; &#x2F;&gt; &lt;em&gt;User interface of WriteHeight showing the 2D heightmap (top-left, inset) and the resultant 3D mesh (main).&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, one of the most intuitive paths for transitioning from drawing in 2D to modelling in 3D is the &lt;strong&gt;heightmap&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;.
While this approach has its limitations, I think it is a good entry-point to 3D that can produce interesting results.
A heightmap is simply a 2D greyscale image, with an x- and a y-axis.
The relative lightness of pixels in that 2D image can be converted to vertex heights in a 3D model, yielding the third z-axis.
Black pixels become the lowest regions in the model and white pixels the highest regions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;existing-software&quot;&gt;Existing Software&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most software with 3D capabilities, including dedicated modellers like Blender and game engines like &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;unity.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Unity&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, can generate models from heightmaps; however, if this is all that you want to achieve they are probably overkill.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A separate application is usually required to make the grayscale image that will be transformed into a 3D model.
There are dedicated applications for generating heightmaps from real terrain elevation data, such as &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;tangrams.github.io&#x2F;heightmapper&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Tangram Heightmapper&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Another approach is that of
&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;archive.org&#x2F;details&#x2F;jsplacement-1.3.0-allplatforms_202108&quot;&gt;JSplacement&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which generates random heightmaps from &lt;em&gt;greebles&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, smaller grayscale parts that are arranged and combined into larger heightmaps.
With a modern digital drawing app like &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;krita.org&#x2F;en&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Krita&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; the range of possible heightmaps is only limited by your skill and imagination.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ephtracy&#x27;s &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;ephtracy.github.io&#x2F;index.html?page=aerialod&quot;&gt;Aerialod&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is dedicated to the specific task of rendering 3D models from heightmaps and comes with a range of options to generate beautiful renders.
Most of my initial heightmap experimentation started with Aerialod, due to its elegance and simplicity.
However, I am now a Linux-user and at time-of-writing Aerialod is only available as a Windows-only download.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my purposes, I wanted something that was:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dedicated to making 3D models from heightmaps&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accessible on any device (computer, tablet, phone)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Useable in a browser with no download required&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;writeheight&quot;&gt;WriteHeight&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an application WriteHeight is simple.
It opens with a viewport showing a random 3D model, which can be inspected using mouse, touch or arrow keys.
The corresponding 2D image from which the model was generated is shown inset.
The 3D model is rendered using the &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.babylonjs.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;babylon.js&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; game engine.
Buttons are included below the viewport, one allows for the generation of further random models from a finite collection.
Another allows a user to upload their own heightmap image, which will then be rendered into an inspectable 3D model.
Models can then be downloaded in different formats, including &lt;code&gt;.stl&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; (good for 3D printing) and &lt;code&gt;.glb&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; (good for 3D rendering).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For convenience, two &lt;em&gt;very basic&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; tools are provided with WriteHeight to generate and download heightmaps.
Clicking the &lt;code&gt;pencil&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; button opens a greyscale drawing tool — this reflects the initial goal of &lt;strong&gt;Write&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;Height, which was to &lt;em&gt;write&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; heightmaps that could be converted into 3D.
Clicking the &lt;code&gt;walking&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; button opens a random walk visualisation that algorithmically generates a grayscale image --- this reflects an ambition for WriteHeight to (eventually) offer a set of simple algorithms for the procedural design of 3D models.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;memory-problems&quot;&gt;Memory Problems&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a self-taught programmer and try to learn by making projects.
My academic job involves no programming and also leaves me with little time to actually write programs.
While I would not say that &lt;em&gt;I am a programmer&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; it is the case that &lt;em&gt;I do programming&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.
In general, I find it more productive and therapeutic to focus on what I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; rather than what I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; when working on hard problems.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I like about programming as an activity is the immediacy of the feedback loop.
It is satisfying to see a nice output like a rendered 3D object but finding bugs can also be a salient reminder that there is much left to learn.
If the bug is in a live application then one is left with a constant aching reminder to figure it out.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had encountered the concept of a &lt;strong&gt;memory leak&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; in the abstract during my messy self-teaching process.
It was difficult for me to appreciate why exactly I should care until it slapped me in the face while working on WriteHeight.
This is a real issue with the current version and has compelled me to begin exploring the role of memory management in effective programming.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the application is initially run everything works great.
The performance is fast and the model can be downloaded in different formats.
Load a second and third model, however, and problems arise.
Each time a model is loaded the previous model &lt;em&gt;visually&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; disappears, which is the intended result; yet, the performance of the application also degrades slightly.
Now if you click &lt;code&gt;download&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; you will get a copy of the visible model but also the previous models that have &amp;quot;disappeared&amp;quot;.
In other words, the previous models are no longer being rendered but still somehow &lt;em&gt;exist in memory&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.
Memory is leaked each time a new model is generated.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application is written in JavaScript, which is infamous for enabling programmers to quickly make something interesting (&amp;quot;cool, a 3D model in the browser!&amp;quot;) while causing themselves future pain (&amp;quot;I want them to download one model not eight!&amp;quot;).
JavaScript is a &lt;em&gt;garbage-collected&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; language that is supposed to automatically handle the freeing of memory.
In WriteHeight, when a model is created it will occupy some memory.
Ideally, when I replace that model with a new one, the garbage collector will automatically reclaim memory from the first model.
Clearly, this is not happening, and the models continue to occupy memory.
For some reason the garbage collector is not effectively identifying the garbage that needs to be collected.
For this to be fixed the functioning of the garbage collector needs to be interrogated and massaged, but garbage-collected languages do not make this easy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Programming is replete with these painful and enlightening lessons.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I now plan to get more familiar with languages that facilitate &lt;em&gt;manual&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; memory management, to get a better intuition for how memory issues are prevented outside of the rarified context of web development.
&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;edibotopic&#x2F;sqong&quot;&gt;Sqong&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a tiny project I made in one such language (&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;odin-lang.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Odin&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;).
It is just a modest clone of &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Pong&quot;&gt;Pong&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which nonetheless provides the rare satisfaction of hearing my own mouth noises soundtrack the collision of a ball off walls and paddles.
It has been quite therapeutic writing code for a small project without needing to think about how the application will run on different browsers and devices.
It is almost certain that Sqong has issues that I am not aware of that I will soon learn from.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of my messy, self-directed journey through programming has involved web-based projects.
This has yielded some nice, shareable projects.
I increasingly think — however — that my work could be improved with a stronger handle on fundamentals like memory management.
That may require forgetting about the web as a target for a while.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Valuing the Merely Interesting</title>
		<published>2023-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2023-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <summary>&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve been contemplating whether there is a place for the &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; interesting in research and teaching.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</summary>
		<link href="https://edibotopic.com/blog/on-interestingness/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://edibotopic.com/blog/on-interestingness/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve been contemplating whether there is a place for the &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; interesting in research and teaching.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;continue-reading&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years ago an academic journal named &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.journalofcontroversialideas.org&quot;&gt;The Journal of Controversial Ideas&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; was created. It offers a platform for authors to explore ideas that traditional outlets might reject due to their controversial nature. That a &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; controversial idea would not necessarily warrant academic publication seems unproblematic. We can assume, however, that this new journal is not intended to platform &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; controversial ideas. The editors are likely seeking presentations of ideas that are both controversial &lt;em&gt;and&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; valuable in some way. The &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; qualifier does a lot of work here and elsewhere. Take the philosopher Kant&#x27;s &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;plato.stanford.edu&#x2F;entries&#x2F;kant-moral&quot;&gt;second formulation of his categorical imperative&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So act that you use humanity, whether in your own person or in the person of any other, always at the same time as an end, never &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; as a means&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Kant&#x27;s ethics we should not treat individuals (and ourselves) as &lt;em&gt;mere&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; means but as &lt;em&gt;ends&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in themselves. The student of ethics prematurely dismisses this maxim as &amp;quot;unrealistic&amp;quot;, insofar as we must frequently use people when conducting a variety of daily tasks. While Kantian ethics prohibits instrumentalising people it does not forbid us from paying for services or asking for favours. These routine social interactions can be navigated successfully without disregarding the dignity of others. During business hours, we may use a worker as a means of obtaining some service but we should also reimburse them fairly and treat them with respect. If we were to meet again outside of that specific business context then it would be inappropriate for us to continue to treat that individual as a worker by asking them to provide that same service. In such a way we can treat someone as a means but usually not as a &lt;em&gt;mere&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; means, while — in contrast — we use an object like a hammer &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; as a tool and pay it no higher deference.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On encountering the new journal I imagined a better journal might have been &lt;em&gt;The Journal of Interesting Ideas&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. The title would itself be a more controversial gesture to the academic world, as it suggests that the existing ecosystem of journals is somewhat &lt;em&gt;biased against interesting ideas&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. This might be a surprising claim, given that we surely expect academic journals to support and encourage interesting ideas. Writing a scientific paper that is interesting, however, is usually a necessary but not sufficient condition for it to be publishable. Most of my professional work is in science, where journals are unlikely to publish an interesting hypothesis unless it is accompanied by a sound theoretical foundation and&#x2F;or rigorous attempt at experimental falsification. Scientific journals then would appear to have a reasonable bias against the &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; interesting, just as they have a reasonable bias against the &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; controversial. When someone advocates for more research in &lt;em&gt;basic&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; science or the pursuit of &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;theconversation.com&#x2F;academics-fear-the-value-of-knowledge-for-its-own-sake-is-diminishing-75341&quot;&gt;knowledge-for-knowledge&#x27;s sake&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; they usually do so in the tacit expectation that such work will be conducted in adherence with standards of rigor and therefore not suffer the fate of being &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; interesting.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the work described is [merely] interesting it is not publishable in its current form.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— A common reviewer comment in a rejection letter&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do sometimes wonder if more attention ought to be given to the &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; interesting in discussions of science, as it so often &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;web.mit.edu&#x2F;redingtn&#x2F;www&#x2F;netadv&#x2F;SP20151130.html&quot;&gt;provides the inspiration for scientific discovery&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and sustains it through prolonged periods of frustration and difficulty. Experiments yield interesting scientific facts but only after an interesting question has first been asked. There are innumerable scientific ideas swirling in the minds of scientists and echoing through the corridors of science departments, many of which might go unexplored for a variety of practical reasons. They exist in the realm of the &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; interesting, relegated to coffee speculations and classroom tangents. Even in fallow periods, with a desperate lack of funding and&#x2F;or personnel, it is an essential aspect of the scientist&#x27;s job to &lt;em&gt;become interested&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in something and find a means of developing that interest. A &lt;em&gt;Journal of Merely Interesting Ideas&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; could be useful in such cases. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least in science, there is little pedagogical treatment of the notion of &lt;em&gt;interestingness&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in the development of an idea. Students are drilled in how to conduct experiments but not how to find or identify interesting scientific questions. A student will sometimes become perplexed when I invite them to &amp;quot;find what interests you&amp;quot; in a scientific work, as if pleading with me to explain &lt;em&gt;what it means to find something &amp;quot;interesting&amp;quot; in science&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. I am reminded of the French semiotician Roland Barthes&#x27; distinction between the &lt;em&gt;studium&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (the set of elements in a work and the context of its presentation) and the &lt;em&gt;punctum&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (a piercing detail in a work that moves or intrigues) in &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Camera_lucida&quot;&gt;Camera Lucida: Reflections on Photography&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. All scientific papers have the same basic structure and ask a typically narrow set of questions in relation to a specific problem (&lt;em&gt;studium&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;) but some papers owe their longevity to a minor detail, throwaway comment or experimental error that attracts the interest of the scientific reader (&lt;em&gt;punctum&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;). It might be unfair to expect students to be familiar with this unusual manner of reading, especially when it typically goes unarticulated.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It does not seem to me that science in any strict way &lt;em&gt;depends&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; on controversy, at least not as much as it depends on interestingness. There are — of course — famous examples of the stifled pursuit of ideas that were deemed controversial (&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.newscientist.com&#x2F;article&#x2F;mg13618460-600-vatican-admits-galileo-was-right&#x2F;&quot;&gt;see the Galileo affair&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;), which compel us to protect the free pursuit of ideas and to remain cautious about unchecked institutional power. Yet, while controversy can certainly be an impediment to the pursuit or expression of an idea, the greatest impediment of all is simply to never become interested in an idea in the first instance. It would perhaps be a greater historical tragedy if Galileo had failed to become sufficiently motivated to make discoveries as he looked upon the universe with disinterest.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>In Your Own Words: On Plagiarism Post-Covid</title>
		<published>2022-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <summary>&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve been thinking about student plagiarism since universities have mostly returned to normal following the Covid-19 pandemic.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</summary>
		<link href="https://edibotopic.com/blog/on-plagiarism/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://edibotopic.com/blog/on-plagiarism/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve been thinking about student plagiarism since universities have mostly returned to normal following the Covid-19 pandemic.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;continue-reading&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;note warning&quot;&gt;
    &lt;i class=&quot;ri-alarm-warning-line ri-lg&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;i&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caution&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;This was written shortly after the educational sector returned to relative normalcy following the Covid-19 pandemic and just before ChatGPT sent it back into a doom spiral.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;

    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students plagiarise, professors get mad and universities draft policies. AI-based essay generators emerge and people begin to use them. Somewhere, an entrepreneur dreams of proctor drones monitoring online exams. What if many students &lt;em&gt;don&#x27;t want to plagiarise&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, but they simply &lt;em&gt;do not know how&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; to write with originality? Maybe plagiarism is just a symptom of inadequate preparation rather than generational laziness or an emerging digital dystopia. Here I consider the particular case of science education.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-facts&quot;&gt;The Facts&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In their first year at university students in a typical science degree are confronted with a bewildering array of &lt;em&gt;facts&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. A student in a given discipline might be expected to develop a foundational knowledge in chemistry, physics and biology by the end of their first year. They are mostly taught about &lt;em&gt;what is known&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;: $x$ is a fact, $y$ is a law, $z$ is a method, and so on.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When learning what it means &lt;em&gt;to do science&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; students learn primarily through group teaching labs. Here they are given recipes to prepare chemicals and instructions outlining the precise steps to follow. Increasingly, their scientific results must be written up according to a rigid &lt;em&gt;template&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Marks are awarded according to rubric that establishes in advance what what it means for an answer to be correct.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;mind-numbing-strategies&quot;&gt;Mind-numbing Strategies&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The student at this point might be forgiven for assuming that science consists of reading procedures, reciting facts and following instructions. More cynical academics might even argue that this is true for those (majority of) scientists who subsequently find themselves with a career in industry. If some boss will one day give them precise instructions in how to do their job then their working life will resemble a template too.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At times something &lt;em&gt;extra&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is asked of the student, however. They might need to write essays or — more commonly — &lt;em&gt;literature reviews&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Literature reviews are useful for anyone seeking to understand a research area. If the popular notion of &lt;em&gt;doing your own research&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; meant &lt;em&gt;do your own literature review&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; we might be in a better place as a society. A &lt;em&gt;good&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; review is not merely a summary of facts but an integration of those facts into a balanced whole. It is not just a set of established answers but a base from which to &lt;em&gt;ask new interesting questions&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A successful review then might allow us to &lt;em&gt;confirm&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; what is scientifically known, &lt;em&gt;integrate&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; ideas from different primary sources, and &lt;em&gt;design&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; new research programmes. Creativity is required to achieve these aims and to makes plans informed by this new knowledge. It is with this kind of project that students are warned most severely about plagiarism. Exhaustive tutorials are provided on how to appropriately cite and reference. Someone taps a finger on a scary policy document. Unfortunately, many students then come to view writing as — above all — an exercise in avoiding plagiarism. Mind-numbing strategies are adopted in response:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get below 20% on the plagiarism detection software I need to copy and paste a sentence but then re-arrange it, change 3-4 words and repeat this until I hit the word limit&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process barely resembles what we understand as &lt;em&gt;writing&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, does not allow the student to develop their own ideas and results in an incoherent experience for the unfortunate reader. Yet, it might well be a rational and effective strategy if success is defined narrowly as the avoidance of a positive hit on the plagiarism detector. This leaves the academic with little recourse: the facts are &lt;em&gt;The Facts&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; after all, right?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;templates-all-the-way-down&quot;&gt;Templates All the Way Down&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some ways these students are set up for failure (as writers).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They have been drilled in the &lt;em&gt;recall&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; of facts but at some point they are expected to be astute and original thinkers. They are motivated &lt;em&gt;negatively&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; by warnings to avoid infringements on academic etiquette rather than being motivated &lt;em&gt;positively&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; by the opportunity to do original work and ask interesting questions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; state opinions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flowery writing is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; appropriate.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plagiarism is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; allowed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are academics who think that these capacities are best developed at postgraduate level &lt;em&gt;once the foundations have been laid&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (whatever that means). For them there is no &lt;em&gt;expectation&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; that an undergraduate might have an original insight. The notion that graduate-entry positions at companies are thought to involve merely &lt;em&gt;following orders&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; further disincentivises academics from exploring student creativity and innovation. Even if students in STEM pursue postgraduate work the projects themselves will typically have been conceived and funded by their prospective supervisor.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s templates all the way down.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;syntax-games&quot;&gt;Syntax Games&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue of plagiarism was discussed with renewed &lt;del&gt;rigour&lt;&#x2F;del&gt; vigour when universities closed because of Covid-19. Students who would normally do exams under supervision in a physical location were now doing them online. In many cases exams that were traditionally closed-book were now open-book, as students referring to their notes could not be (easily) policed. What transpired was that a significant number of students copied answers directly from reference materials. This ignited debates about digital proctoring technology that could prevent students from copying materials or collaborating on answers. Plagiarism came to be associated in the minds of many academics as an inherent flaw of the online exam.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From my discussions with students at the time I gathered that they often simply &lt;em&gt;did not know how to write with originality&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. To paraphrase a common query from students: &amp;quot;if a fact is a fact, then how am I supposed to write it differently?&amp;quot;. Students are commonly advised to read and then rewrite &amp;quot;in their own words&amp;quot; but this is a fatally vague instruction. Essentially it means: re-state what you have read with all of the essential facts intact and a few small insertions and removals. This tends to result in butchered writing that contains the same &lt;em&gt;semantic content&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; as the original but with drastically reduced readability. It is arguably more an exercise in syntax than science, which asks:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How good are you at re-arranging words while maintaining the meaning of a sentence?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;does-plagiarism-exist-if-it-isn-t-detected&quot;&gt;Does Plagiarism Exist if it isn&#x27;t Detected?&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The students who were most frustrated during this period were those that had developed exam preparation techniques that previously sufficed but were now considered plagiarism. A popular exam preparation technique is to memorise large sections of class notes and readings. In an exam hall, the student then identifies the question where a memorised chunk would be most relevant and reproduces it as faithfully as possible on paper. If plagiarism is the repurposing of original content without reference to the source materials then this would appear to be plagiarism. However, it is not usually considered plagiarism. Why? I have heard three responses given by academics:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Answers written on paper are not put through a plagiarism detector&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At least the information was recalled in an exam scenario, which is a difficult feat&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Human memory is unreliable, so it is likely the plagiarism wasn&#x27;t perfect&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first point makes judgements of plagiarism contingent on the ease-of-application of a confirming technology. It suggests that something does not exist unless it is measured. Thus, if we stopped screening electronic submissions for plagiarism then plagiarism would cease to exist. Problem solved.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second point places great value on memorisation, which is certainly a useful skill. Few would argue, however, that rote memorisation develops in-depth knowledge of an area (which &lt;em&gt;is&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; surely the purpose of a university education). Furthermore, if we are simply evaluating students on their ability to reproduce ideas on command we should discard the notion of plagiarism altogether, given the prevalence of electronic tools that can augment human memory in most life situations.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third point seems to debase the notion of &amp;quot;originality&amp;quot;. We might expect that university prepares students to think originally with the &lt;em&gt;autonomous and intentional&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; application of reason. On this account, however, students are rewarded for imperfect memorisation that is muddled by &lt;em&gt;randomness and noise&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Students might be &lt;em&gt;original sometimes&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; but &lt;em&gt;always only by accident&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The students who normally patched together chunks of material in memory to be recalled later in an exam hall were now patching the same chunks together in a file that could be copied during an online exam. In terms of how these students prepared for the exams and how their answers were composed there was little material difference. As a matter of policy, however, one was plagiarism and the other was not.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;performing-knowledge&quot;&gt;Performing Knowledge&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subsequently there was a push to return to exams in physical exam halls, on the basis that this led to &amp;quot;better and fairer&amp;quot; exams. In reality, this likely reintroduced the tendency among many students to achieve astonishing feats of memorisation when plagiarising text under the watchful eye of invigilators.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plagiarism and its avoidance is evidently an important issue for academics but there is no clear conception of what constitutes plagiarism, why it is an intellectual vice or how students can be best prepared to avoid the practice. This seems especially true in STEM fields, where the art of writing well is frequently devalued and many of the solutions enacted by academics merely function to disguise or evade the problem. For example, if students are plagiarising in their essays then essays might be replaced by multiple choice questions where students do not have to formulate their own thoughts. If online exams have high amounts of plagiarism then they might be moved to an exam hall where the act of plagiarism becomes an impressive memory trick.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The greatest tragedy in all of this is that generations of scientists are graduating without the instinct or ability to write. I expect that those of us who work in academia will continue to be distracted by new techno-dystopian spectres, like AI-generated student essays, when we might be best served addressing the age-old problem of teaching students that writing is a valuable activity &lt;em&gt;in itself&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. For science undergraduates, writing has become an intricate act of performing knowledge according to academic conventions rather than a useful method of developing one&#x27;s own ideas. As Paul Graham wrote in &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.paulgraham.com&#x2F;essay.html&quot;&gt;The Age of the Essay&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, to write an &lt;em&gt;essay&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; originally meant &lt;em&gt;to try&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;to attempt&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (to figure something out). Such freedom of exploration is not facilitated within the confines of rigid templates and rubrics.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the challenges in persuading students of the value of writing in the academic style is that it is not valued outside of academia. Most students will not become academic researchers and will therefore not need to satisfy the expectations of editors and peer-reviewers. In a research and development role in industry a graduate might be expected to write a literature review but it will not undergo a plagiarism check and is very unlikely to be submitted for publication.
Plagiarism norms reflect the public and communal nature of scholarly work but — as legal scholar Brian Frye &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;deliverypdf.ssrn.com&#x2F;delivery.php?ID=659113087090031103002099105071071095007085007037003090100005000104097069091127067102026056048010010036110094098031094087118012104006091005020064009087030118075087090016005101007009110029066115100029123006089078011010090117031123002117074015081002026&amp;amp;EXT=pdf&amp;amp;INDEX=TRUE&quot;&gt;has pointed out&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; — most student work is evaluated by an academic within the context of a classroom (it is not a public work). There is therefore an apparent disconnect between what motivates the standards for academic plagiarism and the students who must act in accordance with those standards.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;appendix-searching-for-alternatives&quot;&gt;Appendix: Searching for Alternatives&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help students to think critically about the rights and wrongs of plagiarism we might need to provide them with alternative models and case-studies, or at least something other than a &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;deliverypdf.ssrn.com&#x2F;delivery.php?ID=659113087090031103002099105071071095007085007037003090100005000104097069091127067102026056048010010036110094098031094087118012104006091005020064009087030118075087090016005101007009110029066115100029123006089078011010090117031123002117074015081002026&amp;amp;EXT=pdf&amp;amp;INDEX=TRUE&quot;&gt;vaguely-written but extremely consequential&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; academic dishonesty policy document. Art, music and design are replete with examples that are less opaque than academia and definitely more immediately thought-provoking.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people would agree that directly copying a song from another artist and profiting from that copy is morally wrong — the difficulty with applying this model to science is that established scientific facts are taken to be &amp;quot;fixed&amp;quot; in their correct form, which makes it difficult to imagine an alternative means for their expression. The important point for students here is probably that not all scientific statements are statements of established fact; for example, most research papers offer — at most — tentative conclusions and recommendations based on limited data.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The act&#x2F;art of sampling is more of a contested issue than direct reproduction and in some jurisdictions (e.g., the US) &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.mondaq.com&#x2F;unitedstates&#x2F;music-and-the-arts&#x2F;899396&#x2F;drake39s-sampling-is-a-fair-use&quot;&gt;may hinge on the concept of &lt;em&gt;transformative use&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. There have been many famous cases of musicians — especially in hip-hop — being sued for sampling music, even when the song is a distinct creation on its face. This legal threat has led to a chilling effect, with many artists now resorting to &lt;em&gt;interpolation&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; rather than sampling. In this way, an original work is re-performed rather than re-produced. A music student might well be praised for interpolating a melody on their instrument and incorporating it into an otherwise original composition; however, to some degree that student is being assessed on their mastery as an instrumentalist and composer. It is less clear to what extent a scientist is a scientist insofar as they can recite and compose.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am reminded also of the phenomenon of &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.nme.com&#x2F;blogs&#x2F;nme-blogs&#x2F;misheard-song-lyrics-6787&quot;&gt;mondegreens&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, where a lyric, poem or quote is mis-read&#x2F;heard or misinterpreted, yielding an original result — this is maybe the most likely route to originality for the scientific novice who is bewildered by a learned professor. Unfortunately, while a misinterpreted poem might lead to an interesting phrase, a misinterpreted scientific fact is likely to yield a falsity. This is perhaps reminiscent of the situation of the student in the exam hall, who interpolates source material and introduces new imperfections in the process.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, there is the relatively new concept of the &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;tvtropes.org&#x2F;pmwiki&#x2F;pmwiki.php&#x2F;Main&#x2F;VideoGameDemake&quot;&gt;demake&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which is a remake of an original work within significant constraints. For example, a 3D videogame produced with a multi-million budget and a team of hundreds that is designed to run on the latest hardware will be demade into a 2D game by one person so that it runs on hardware from the 1980s. The student — who doesn&#x27;t have a personal laboratory or a team of researchers — operates within constraints that the academic scientist does not.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.paulgraham.com&#x2F;essay.html&quot;&gt;Paul Graham&#x27;s blog on the essay&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=cmr5Qrf_Vn8&quot;&gt;Podcast on plagiarism with Brian Frye&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;papers.ssrn.com&#x2F;sol3&#x2F;papers.cfm?abstract_id=3462144&quot;&gt;Paper on plagiarism by Brian Frye&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Simulating Stoke&#x27;s Law Visually</title>
		<published>2022-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <summary>&lt;p&gt;I built a simple application to teach factors affecting the floating and sedimentation of particles in liquid.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</summary>
		<link href="https://edibotopic.com/blog/stokes-law/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://edibotopic.com/blog/stokes-law/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I built a simple application to teach factors affecting the floating and sedimentation of particles in liquid.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;continue-reading&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many food processes are designed to either promote &lt;em&gt;or&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; prevent the physical separation of particles from liquids. The behaviour governing such separation phenomena is described using an equation known as Stoke&#x27;s Law. Students of food science are familiar with this equation, although it is commonly misunderstood. Technical fixes for the physical instabilities in liquid foods are simple and long-standing, yet are sometimes mistrusted by the public. This short post discusses this equation and a simple interactive animation for developing intuition around the phenomena it describes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;animating-stoke-s-law&quot;&gt;Animating Stoke&#x27;s Law&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;figs&#x2F;stokesLawUI.png&quot; alt=&quot;UI of Stoke&#x27;s Law&quot; title=&quot;UI of StokesLaw&quot; &#x2F;&gt; &lt;em&gt;User interface for Stoke&#x27;s Law simulation showing sliders (top), velocity graph (bottom-left) and statistics (bottom-right). View interactive simulation in &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;edibotopic.github.io&#x2F;stokes-law&#x2F;&quot;&gt;full screen&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or read the &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;edibotopic&#x2F;stokes-law&quot;&gt;source code&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to see the JavaScript implementation (if you&#x27;re so inclined)&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stoke&#x27;s Law describes the sedimentation of particles in suspensions (fruit pulp in orange juice) and the flotation of droplets in emulsions (creaming of milk fat). In food science it is invoked for a variety of purposes. One of the most simple techniques for measuring a liquid&#x27;s viscosity involves using Stoke&#x27;s Law to estimate the value from the rate at which a ball falls through the liquid. The equation is also used to identify the key parameters that influence how a group of particles fall or rise due to gravity, which can be used to develop strategies to make it happen quicker or slower. A version of the equation is shown below describing the separation velocity ($v$) of particles with diameter $D$ in a solvent with viscosity $\mu$ when subject to acceleration due to gravity $g$. The $\Delta \rho$ means the difference ($\Delta$) between the density ($\rho$) of the particle and the solvent.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$v = \frac{D^2 \cdot(\Delta \rho) \cdot g }{18 \cdot \mu}$$&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;techno-functionality&quot;&gt;Techno-functionality&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the technological solutions informed by Stoke&#x27;s Law are the source of routine confusion when &amp;quot;homogenised&amp;quot; is found on a product label or &amp;quot;guar gum&amp;quot; in an ingredients list. Homogenisation is simply a way of physically reducing the size of particles. As the particle diameter value ($D$) in Stoke&#x27;s Law is raised to the power of $2$ it has a significant influence on separation speed. Guar gum is one of a variety of food ingredients that has a purely &lt;em&gt;techno-functional&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; role, which typically involves increasing viscosity ($\mu$) so that friction slows particles down as they move through the liquid. Sometimes it might be desirable to promote instability, such as when whole milk is centrifuged to create skim milk and cream, replacing the acceleration due to gravity ($g$) with that due to centrifugal force ($\omega ^2 r$). These factors become more obvious if you play around with the &lt;em&gt;particle diameter&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;solvent viscosity&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; sliders in the animation. Try the other sliders and you might find some other interesting effects.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;intuition-and-science&quot;&gt;Intuition and Science&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us have a good intuition for these phenomena in an everyday context. We expect large stones to sink faster than small pebbles. We know that the air pockets in a wine bottle cork means that it will tend to float on water. In food, the particles involved are often microscopic, making the behavior less &lt;em&gt;salient&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Showing a static photograph of particles on a microscope slide does not give us a feel for the dynamics involved. If we are uncomfortable with equations then the mathematics of Stoke&#x27;s Law might not help. That&#x27;s why I developed a simple simulation that allows students to manipulate all of the major variables using sliders. I hope this simple &amp;quot;virtual experiment&amp;quot; can improve the intuition of students for the phenomena but also the equation that helps explain them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;figs&#x2F;cream_40X.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Micrograph of shaving cream&quot; title=&quot;micrograph of cream&quot; &#x2F;&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fig. 2.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Micrograph of cream showing its emulsion structure. As the oil droplets are less dense than the water surrounding them they tend to float (credit: edibotopic).&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent years it has become slightly more common for companies to avoid homogenising their products and to cease adding stabilising ingredients. This is not because of any demonstrable health benefit but rather because these products can be marketed as being &amp;quot;more natural&amp;quot;. This is an interesting case of a technological decision (whether to employ stabilising technology) being influenced by a metaphysical judgement (that technologies have degrees of naturalness) that has real business consequences (there is a market for &amp;quot;natural&amp;quot; foods). In any case, whether we buy a physically-unstable smoothie at a health food store or homogenised milk from the supermarket, we can understand both by appeal to Stoke&#x27;s law.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Moving from WordPress</title>
		<published>2022-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2023-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <summary>&lt;p&gt;I moved from WordPress to GitHub to host my blog.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</summary>
		<link href="https://edibotopic.com/blog/site-migrated/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://edibotopic.com/blog/site-migrated/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I moved from WordPress to GitHub to host my blog.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;continue-reading&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;note info&quot;&gt;
    &lt;i class=&quot;ri-information-line ri-lg&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;i&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
        
        &lt;p&gt;This was originally about switching from WordPress to GitHub but also —  by extension — to a Static Site Generator (SSG) in the form of Eleventy. In 2023 I changed from the SSG discussed here — Eleventy (JavaScript) — to Zola (Rust).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;

    &lt;&#x2F;div&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made a website when my academic job began to require more online teaching. The idea was to craft a space for exploring my personal and scholarly interests in a more integrated and informal way. Under time pressure, with little programming experience and a minimal amount of research, I chose &lt;em&gt;WordPress&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; as a publishing platform. This choice made it quick and easy to get a functioning site up-and-running, but creating the content soon became a chore. In parallel, I became a more proficient user of GitHub. For every incomplete blog post there was a new software project in a GitHub repository. For these and other reasons I have decided to migrate the website to GitHub. This post serves to outline my motivations and get this blog started.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-a-website&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why a Website?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I developed a &lt;em&gt;somewhat&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; undeserved reputation as a &amp;quot;tech person&amp;quot; among my university colleagues during the era of Covid lockdowns. Admittedly, it was a period of frantic digital exploration. I sunk countless hours into music, programming and 3D design, among other activities. This was partially motivated by a sense of deep panic: having previously been an &lt;em&gt;occasionally&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; boring lecturer in some of my in-person classes, how could I now avoid giving boring online lectures? The blurry ambition was to model myself on the content creators that I had come to recognise as &lt;em&gt;effective&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; teachers (at least for me &lt;em&gt;personally&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;). There were plans for Youtube videos, personal blogs, bespoke soundtracks, software tools for teaching and a food-themed podcast. &lt;em&gt;Some&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; of these things materialised, and of those that &lt;em&gt;did&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; the website was probably the least successful.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;edibotopic.com&quot;&gt;edibotopic.com&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; — in some way — was an attempt to (re)integrate aspects of my own personality that had been cut adrift during the intense and specialised work characteristic of early-stage academia. My pre-academic life was defined mostly by writing $+$ music (creatively) and sport $+$ gaming (casually). If the creative projects were materially &lt;em&gt;unsuccessful&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and the casual hobbies pleasant &lt;em&gt;distractions&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; they were still rewarding. During the initial years in my academic position (&lt;em&gt;in food science&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;) I earned a philosophy degree — much to the confusion of my colleagues — adding another node in my web of interests. I believe there are many productive and enlightening connections to be made between ideas across different domains of human knowledge, and I needed a place to explore these connections when the structures of academia did not make that possible.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;bad-friction&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bad Friction&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;wordpress.org&quot;&gt;WordPress&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is often recommended to beginners who want to make a website. It has a lot to offer. Choose a name, choose a theme and you&#x27;re on your way. There is a large ecosystem of &lt;strong&gt;plugins&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, which is also very attractive. For example, I was exploring the &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.babylonjs.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Babylon.js&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; game engine for making 3D content for the web and WordPress had a plugin for displaying those scenes. I thought that people might comment on my blog posts and there was a plugin for handling those user interactions. &lt;em&gt;What if someone wanted to make a donation&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; I thought and — sure enough — there was a plugin for that too.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later, I began to find these plugins more troublesome for a few reasons:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the features these plugins add are relatively trivial to implement in a standard website, &lt;em&gt;if&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; you know what you&#x27;re doing. How they often seem to function on WordPress is overcoming the constraints imposed by WordPress itself. Adding interactivity (through scripts) or styling (through CSS) is routine practice when tweaking a website but it is decidedly &lt;em&gt;awkward&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; on WordPress. Plugins overcome this awkwardness but at a cost.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plugins often reduce site performance. Say you want to add support for a photo gallery. As a beginner, you might find some code samples online where this feature is implemented in a few lines of JavaScript and CSS. WordPress, however, makes it difficult to add the necessary code. So, someone recommends a gallery plugin, which you then install. Several weeks later you notice a dip in site performance. The common practice at this point is to uninstall each plugin one-by-one to identify the root cause. Even if this time-consuming, iterative process leads you to identify the culprit you are then left with the hard decision of whether to cull the offending plugin(s) to benefit performance, or sacrifice that performance for the desired functionality.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plugin ecosystem is very much a &lt;em&gt;marketplace&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. You will be surprised to find that seemingly basic features are behind a paywall. You will be prompted for reviews. Your choice to stop using a plugin will be queried. The creators of these plugins are entitled to seek feedback and remuneration for their efforts but if you are using multiple plugins this process can add unnecessary friction to the simple act of writing a blog post.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the plugins that are attractive may not be necessary for meagre use-cases like my own. Writing blogs about niche academic topics was unlikely to attract donations. People were probably not going to fall in love having first met each other in the comments section of one of my blog posts. The ease with which you can add functionalities like these ones can very easily lead to you overpowering your website.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer to these problems is often simply to &amp;quot;use less plugins&amp;quot;, but if the diversity and easy-implementation of plugins were what attracted you in the first place then a major benefit of the platform seems to be undermined by this line of reasoning.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this I know with the benefit of hindsight. The &amp;quot;trivial implementations&amp;quot; I refer to were not trivial for me &lt;em&gt;at the time&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. I did not know what functionality my site would require. In retrospect, I could only ever have started with a tool like WordPress and if I had more complex requirements (e-commerce) then maybe I never would have left. I had chosen &lt;code&gt;wordpress.org&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; as opposed to &lt;code&gt;wordpress.com&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; as the former seemed to offer more immediate possibilities for customisation. This required me to &lt;strong&gt;pay for web hosting&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Similar functionality can be accessed in the &lt;code&gt;.com&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; option if you enter one of WordPress.com&#x27;s &lt;strong&gt;paid tiers&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. While I was &lt;em&gt;paying&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; a significant amount of money for a website that was painful to customise and maintain, my &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;edibotopic&quot;&gt;GitHub profile&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; swelled with freely-hosted web applications.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The alternative for &lt;em&gt;me-as-beginner&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; was building a site from scratch or using a static site generator. These options were beyond my skill-set at the time, or at least beyond my capacity to understand what I was directly manipulating when building the site. So I maintained my unproductive blog, which largely involved the drudgery of updating plugins to prevent security problems. At the same time I was increasingly productive with small software projects on GitHub. Creating these projects on GitHub was &lt;em&gt;more difficult&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; on its face (it involved actual coding), yet it was where I seemed to be making the most ground.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;plugging-out&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Plugging Out&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal grievances with WordPress came to head when I was writing my final blog post, which was a summary of some recent software projects.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the intervening years I had become a fan of editing plain text&#x2F;markdown using (Neo)Vim as my text editor. I would then copy the text and paste it into the WordPress editor. Inevitably this would cause unforeseen formatting issues that would take a considerable amount of time to fix. I had enabled markdown editing in WordPress &lt;em&gt;via&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; a plugin but the post still came out jumbled. I had specific, enraging problems while trying to add a code block, a feature common to most markdown editors&#x2F;previewers that looks like this:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;javascript&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#282a36;color:#f8f8f2;&quot; class=&quot;language-javascript &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot; data-lang=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#6272a4;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; code goes here
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-style:italic;color:#8be9fd;&quot;&gt;let &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ffffff;&quot;&gt;a &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff79c6;&quot;&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bd93f9;&quot;&gt;2
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-style:italic;color:#8be9fd;&quot;&gt;let &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ffffff;&quot;&gt;b &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff79c6;&quot;&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bd93f9;&quot;&gt;6
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-style:italic;color:#66d9ef;&quot;&gt;console&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff79c6;&quot;&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8be9fd;&quot;&gt;log&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ffffff;&quot;&gt;b &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff79c6;&quot;&gt;&#x2F; &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ffffff;&quot;&gt;a&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#6272a4;&quot;&gt;&#x2F;&#x2F; returns 3
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ended up installing three different plugins before I found something that worked and the results &lt;em&gt;still&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; looked bad. Due to these and other issues, every time I sat down to write something there was a little bit of dread associated with the publishing stage. As writing is already difficult enough, the (bad) friction introduced by the WordPress editor was a problem.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;good-friction&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good Friction&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plain text. The terminal. Text editors. Version control.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Terms that are superficially bland but that are known to excite many programmers. Like most &lt;em&gt;non-programmers&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, I was originally mystified as to why these were interesting or useful, not to mind &lt;em&gt;exciting&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. I gradually came to understand their appeal, and I hope to discuss these topics in more depth in future posts. For now, it is enough to say that I greatly value the customisability and speed of a good text editor, as well as the structured and transparent nature of a version-controlled project. When creating material for a website I wanted to leverage these tools. Like &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;noelle.dev&#x2F;meta&#x2F;about&quot;&gt;others before me&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; I decided to make the switch from WordPress to a static site generator.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This website took longer to setup than if I was using WordPress. Like most static site generators the idea is simple: to take content written in markdown and convert it into web pages. The site is &lt;em&gt;static&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; as opposed to &lt;em&gt;dynamic&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; because I want to show all users the same content rather than tailor the site based on data from individual users — as a result, the static version of &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;edibotopic.com&quot;&gt;edibotopic.com&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is faster then the dynamic WordPress version and I am prevented from adding annoying&#x2F;unnecessary features that &amp;quot;personalise&amp;quot; the user experience. Most of my interaction with the site should basically proceed as follows:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open a terminal&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write &lt;code&gt;.md&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; file &lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run &lt;code&gt;npm run build&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Push&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; changes to GitHub&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The markdown is a straightforward way of formatting text:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;markdown&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#282a36;color:#f8f8f2;&quot; class=&quot;language-markdown &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-markdown&quot; data-lang=&quot;markdown&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8be9fd;&quot;&gt;# Good Friction
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Plain text. The terminal...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Terms that are...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff79c6;&quot;&gt;. &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Open terminal
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff79c6;&quot;&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; Write markdown...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;The markdown is a straightforward way of formatting text:
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;build&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; process, however, involves multiple interacting parts:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Site generator&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: eleventy&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bundler&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Vite&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Markdown parser&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: markdown-it&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CSS tools&#x2F;frameworks&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: tailwind, PostCSS&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Package manager&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: NPM&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides obvious tasks like styling the website to my preferences, there were innumerable tiny problems to solve associated with these different parts.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original bundler had been deprecated so I had to migrate to Vite. List numbers&#x2F;bullets were being rendered incorrectly and I needed to learn Tailwind configuration to fix them. Several issues were associated with outdated dependencies that needed to be updated or upgraded through &lt;code&gt;NPM&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;. My &lt;em&gt;production build&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; did not behave like my &lt;em&gt;development build&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; because of how GitHub handles relative paths.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even when addressing these issues took time the solution usually &lt;em&gt;made sense&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, rather than being some &lt;em&gt;deus ex machina&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in the form of a plugin. While I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; use plugins on this site they are less abundant and often merely implement small adjustments to how an &lt;code&gt;.md&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; file is converted into &lt;code&gt;.html&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My major gripe with static site generators is how they appear &lt;em&gt;as a code base&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; to the uninitiated. In the other software projects I have worked on I like the idea that someone can look at the code and see a simple directory structure like so:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#282a36;color:#f8f8f2;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;+--scripts
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;+--styles
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;+--index.html
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Static site generators create relatively complex directory structures. In addition, different people use different JAM (JavaScript APIs Markup) &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;jamstack.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;stacks&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. While I use &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.11ty.dev&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Eleventy&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; another will use &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;gohugo.io&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Hugo&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, with subtly different APIs, dependencies and directory structures in each case. If you like a feature of a static site and want to study it there can be a lot of detective work involved. From a pedagogical standpoint this is undesirable, especially if a prospective student is not already a web developer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, I needed something compact that I could manage and understand &lt;em&gt;if only in principle&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. When something breaks it would be within my power to investigate and fix it, rather than endlessly searching forums for workarounds.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While my instinct for colour schemes might not be perfect — you can be the judge — this site looks &lt;em&gt;at least as good&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; as the WordPress one to my eyes, and I am in more control of how that might change in the future.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-plan&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Plan&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people have a difficulty with &lt;em&gt;starting writing&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, while I have a difficulty &lt;em&gt;stopping writing&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. I have a natural tendency to write articles that are long, verbose and that try to do too much.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example 1&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: my final blog on the previous site, which attempted to summarise 6-7 software projects I had worked on. Of course, this could have simply been 6-7 shorter and more self-contained blog posts.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example 2&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: this very post.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming from academia, I am also a prodigious editor. An article requiring 5 or even 12 drafts is &lt;em&gt;normal&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; to me. This, however, is not sustainable when maintaining a &amp;quot;casual&amp;quot; blog. The whole idea here is to write more freely and fluently, even if a post ends up on &lt;em&gt;Hacker News&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and its exacting users decry the state of internet writing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major goal of mine with this site is to write more regularly but also more concisely, with this blog perhaps being a bad start in that respect! In addition, it will function as a reference for my recent and active projects in music, software and technology. Lastly, if my nascent multimedia projects (video, podcasting) come to fruition then I will incorporate them into this site.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>